Inventory of the Philip Howerton Papers 1812-1870
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Philip Howerton Papers, 1812-1870.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 H84
148 items.
Papers, 1812-1870, of Philip Howerton and his family of Halifax County, Virginia. Includes a letterbook, 1829-1853; account books, 1825-1857, of the store and blacksmith's shop of Philip Howerton and tobacco manufacturing company of Philip Howerton and W. M. Howerton.
Philip Howerton,; W. M. Howerton,; Mat. Cabaniss,; Howerton Family. Author: Cabaniss, Mat.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 148 items, 06/04/1940.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1812-1870, of Philip Howerton and his family of Halifax County, Va. Includes a letterbook, 1829-1853; account books, 1825-1857, of the store and blacksmith's shop of Philip Howerton and tobacco manufacturing company of Philip Howerton and W. M. Howerton.
The collection also includes accounts, 1852-1859, for transporting tobacco; sermons, 1832 and n.d., of Charles Busser; constitution and minutes of the Branch Bible Society of Halifax County, Va.; letter, 1834, from American Tract Society; part of one of the manuscript volumes contains accounts of orphans (of Mat Cabaniss) who were wards of Philip Howerton, and a contract between Philip Howerton and a former slave family in 1865-1866.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into seven series: 1. Tobacco Receipts, 2. Circulars, 3. A Contract and Legal Papers, 4. Religious Writtings, 5. Letters, 6. Miscellaneous, and 7. Personal Accounts of Philip Howerton.
Arrangement
The series are arranged by date.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Howerton family.
Persons:
Howerton, W. M.; Cabaniss, Mat.
Subjects:
Orphans--United States.; Tobacco--Virginia-- History--19th century.
Geographical Names:
Halifax County (Va.)--History--19th century.
Contents List
  Series 1: Tobacco Receipts
- Receipts for transporting tobacco, 1852-1859., 27 items. (Folder 1)
  The tobacco was transported from South Boston, Virginia, via Roanoke River to Weldon, North Carolina, then via Seaboard and Roanoke Railroad to Norfolk.
  Series 2: Circulars
- A New York publication, Tobacco Circular, on conditions in the world tobacco market, 1852-1853., 2 items. (Folder 2)
  Series 3: A Contract and Legal Papers
- A Contract and legal papers, 1866-1865., 10 items. (Folder 3)
  Contract between Philip Howerton and a former slave, his sons and wife, for work on the plantation in 1866, 1865.
  Series 4: Religious Writings
- Religious Writings, 1829-1839, n.d., 4 items. (Folder 4)
  - Manuscript sermons by Rev. Charles Dusser, 8 January 1832, n.d., 2 items. Manuscripts. (Folder 4)
  - Manuscript talk on the state of society, 1839., 4 pages. (Folder 4)
  - Constitution and Minutes of the Branch Bible Society of Halifax County, Virginia, 12 July 1829. (Folder 4)
  Series 5: Letters
- Letters, 1834-1862., 39 items. (Folder 5)
  - Letter from the American Tract Society, 14 January 1834., 3 pages. (Folder 5)
  - Accounts of tobacco shipments from South Boston, Virginia to Norfolk and shift to shipping by railroad to Richmond, 1852-1853. (Folder 5)
  - Typescript copy of letter from Henry A. Wise to his granddaughter, Harriet E. Howerton, 25 October 1862., 1 page. Typescript. (Folder 5)
  - Accounts of debts, payments, and requests for goods and/or services, various, n.d. (Folder 5)
    Several letters are from Mr. Tuberville, and Mr. Frothingham.
  - Thank you note from Jonathan McLang to [Philip Howerton?], 16 November, 1823., 1 page. (Folder 5)
    Letter thanks the recipient and asks that the recipient would "please send my horse by the boy, Cubb and direct him..."the safest means by which he can get home with as little injury to the horse as probable." The back of the letter has various figures and equations written on it.
  - Printed sheets from the College of William and Mary, n.d., 3 items. (Folder 5)
    Item is asking for contributions to met the growing needs of its students based upon the contributions the College has made to America. Dr. W. A. Goodwin is the director of the Endowment Campaign.
  Series 6: Miscellaneous items
- Miscellaneous items, n.d., 21 items. (Folder 6)
  Most items appear to be figures, accounts and equations.
  Series 7: Personal accounts of Philip Howerton
- Personal accounts of Philip Howerton, 1812-1870. (Folder 7)
  - Personal Accounts of Philip Howerton, 1812-1868., 31 pieces. (Folder 7)
  - Manuscript volume and account book No. 1, 1821, 1825-1828., 60 pages. 13"x8" (Volume MsV. 1)
    Manuscript volumes, No.1 mathematics textbook of Charles H. Cabaniss. Back portion of the book was used by Philip Howerton, Halifax County merchant as an account book.
  - Manuscript Book No. 2, 1849-1857. (Volume MsV. 2)
    - Store, blacksmith and tobacco firm account book, 1849-1950., 44 pages. (Volume MsV. 2)
      This hand stitched book is inset into the larger manuscript volume, the first 16 pages of which are used to show tobacco engaged and of whom engaged, by Philip and W.M. Howteron, tobacco manufacturers, 1849- 1850. The following 28 pages show the accounts for Philip Howerton's store and blacksmith shop, 1851-1854.
    - Account book of Philip Howerton, Halifax County, Virginia, 1823-1869., 109 pages. 12"x8" (Volume MsV. 2)
      Part of the accounts are in his capacity as guardian of the orphaned children of Mat Cabaniss.
  - Manuscript Book No. 3, 1849-1853., 354 pages. 12"x8" (Volume MsV. 3)
    Letter copy book and shipping records of the firm of Philip and William M. Howerton, Halifax County, Virginia, tobacco manufactures.
  - Microfilm of a manuscript account book, 1842-1846., 1 reel. Microfilm. Negatives. (Othertype M-96)
    First part of book is used by Philip Howerton as an account book, 1842-1845, and the latter part is used as a cash book by Philip Howerton and W.M. Cabaniss, 1844-1846.
    The original is privately owned. A descriptive page of this microfilm is included in this collection.